Florence Guertin Tuttle Papers, 1917-1948
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Florence Guertin Tuttle papers
1917-1948
Florence Guertin Tuttle
163
8 boxes (3.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
The bulk of this collection consists of writings and speeches, research material, and records from Tuttle's involvement in organizations such as the American Association for International Cooperation, the American Union Against Militarism, the Women's Peace Party, and the League of Nations, among others, circa 1910s-1940s. Major themes include peace, internationalism, birth control rights, suffrage, women's clubs, and women writers. Significant correspondents include Virginia Gildersleeve, Florence Lamont, Anna Garlin Spencer, and Portia Willis (Berg) Fitzgerald. There is a small amount of biographical material, photographs, memorabilia, and family correspondence; and Tuttle's unpublished autobiography (1948).
Florence Guertin Tuttle was born in Brooklyn, New York in 1869 to Lucy Henry, a descendent of Patrick Henry, and Pierre Guertin, a merchant and French-Canadian immigrant. Educated at a small private school, the Nassau Institute, Guertin was an avid reader and a prolific writer of poems and stories. As a young adult, Guertin was involved in one of the first women's clubs, the Avitas Club, where she was exposed to speakers such as Charlotte Perkins Gilman. In her late twenties she married Frank Day Tuttle (Yale class of 1887) and the couple settled in Brooklyn Heights, New York. Their sons, Day and Guertin Tuttle, were born in 1902 and 1904. When the children were small, Tuttle devoted part of her time to many causes including women's suffrage, the Woman's Peace Party and birth control. In 1915 she published The Awakening of Woman: Suggestions from the Psychic Side of Feminism and in 1917 a collection of stories entitled Give My Love to Maria.
Devastated by the horrors of World War I, Tuttle became a strong advocate for internationalism. In this new role she became Chair of the Women's Pro-League Council in 1920 and attended numerous meetings of the Council of the League of Nations in Geneva. There she befriended many important people such as First Lady Edith Bolling Wilson and Carrie Chapman Catt. During this time she also wrote Women and World Federation (1919) as well as numerous articles and leaflets on world cooperation, economic causes of war, and the League of Nations. In 1932 she was selected by Carrie Chapman Catt to be a delegate to the Disarmament Conference in Geneva. Tuttle was in great demand as a speaker about peace and internationalism. She became the Executive Chairman of the Greater New York Branch of the League of Nations Non-Partisan Association in 1924 and published two more books, including Alternatives to War (1931) before her death in 1951.
The Florence Guertin Tuttle Papers include writings, speeches, research materials, and organizational records. Documents pertain to Tuttle's involvement in organizations such as the American Association for International Cooperation, the American Union Against Militarism, the Woman's Peace Party, and the League of Nations, among others, from the 1910s to the 1940s. Major themes include peace, internationalism, birth control rights, suffrage, women's clubs, and women writers. There is a small amount of biographical material, photographs, memorabilia, and family correspondence; and Tuttle's unpublished autobiography (1948). Notable correspondents include Virginia Gildersleeve, Florence Lamont, Anna Garlin Spencer, and Portia Willis (Berg) Fitzgerald.
This collection is organized into four series:
BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
CORRESPONDENCE
WRITINGS AND SPEECHES
ORGANIZATIONS AND CONFERENCES
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Frank Day Tuttle donated his mother's papers to the Sophia Smith Collection from 1951-62. Reprocessed by Kelsey Radwilowicz, 2007.
Fitzgerald, Portia Willis--Correspondence; Gildersleeve, Virginia Crocheron, 1877--Correspondence; Lamont, Florence Haskell Corliss, 1873-52--Correspondence; Spencer, Anna Garlin, 1851-31--Correspondence; Tuttle, Florence Guertin, 1869-1951; League of Nations--History--Sources; Woman's Peace Party; Women--International cooperation--History--Sources; Feminists--United States--Biography--Sources; Peace Movements--History--20th century--Sources; Women and peace--History--20th century--Sources; Women's rights--History--20th century-Sources
APPENDIX: League of Nations Publications
Pamphlets (box 7, folders 6-7)
The Political Activities of the League, No. 83, 1922
Austria, What the League Has Done for Austria, No. 136, 1923
The Technique of the League of Nations by Roth Williams, No. 144, 1924
Annual Report of the Executive Committee to the General Council of the League of Nations Union for the Year Ending 31st December 1923, No. 147, 1924
British Business and the League, No. 149, 1924
Human Welfare and the League, No. 155, 1924
Five Years' Treaties (1919 -23), No. 156, 1924
Labour and the League of Nations, including a defense of the International Labour Organisation by The Right Honourable J. Ramsay MacDonald, M.P., No. 157, 1924
Lantern Lecture on the League of Nations, No. 159, 1924
How the League of Nations Union Spends Its Money, Being a Summary of the Annual Report for 1925, No. 160, 1924
An Experiment in a Secondary School, No. 162, n.d.
Geneva 1924 (Fifth Assembly of the League of Nations), No. 164, n.d.
The Complete Text of the Covenant and the Geneva Protocol, No. 165, 1924
The Covenant and the Protocol by Sir Frederick Pollock, 1924
Lord Grey of Fallodon on the Geneva Protocol, No. 170, 1925
Chemical Warfare, No. 171, 1925
The "Labour Covenant" (Part XIII of the Treaty of Versailles), No. 172, Jan 1925
League of Nations Union Policy (An Address delivered at a Meeting of the General Council of the League of Nations Union by Professor Gilbert Murray, LL.D., D.Litt., December 19, 1924), No. 173, 1925
The Meaning of the Protocol by H. Wilson Harris, No. 175, 1925
The Governments of Britain, France, Czechoslovakia and Canada on the Geneva Protocol, No. 177, 1925
Geneva 1925 (being an account of the Sixth Assembly of the League of Nations), by H. Wilson Harris
International Conciliation, "The Problem of Minorities": articles by Louis Eisenmann, William E. Rappard, H. Wilson Harris, and Raymond Leslie Buell, 1926
International Conciliation, "Disarmament and American Foreign Policy": articles by James T. Shotwell, Tasker H. Bliss, David Hunter Miller, and Joseph P. Chamberlain, 1926
League of Nations, "America and the Permanent Court of International Justice": Vol. V, No. 5
International Conciliation, "The Political Doctrine of Fascism" by Alfredo Rocco, Minister of Justice in the Government of Italy, Oct, 1926
World Peace Foundations Pamphlets, "Handbook on the League of Nations (1920-1924)": Vol. VII, No. 3-4, 1924 (2 copies)
World Peace Foundations Pamphlets, "Hearings on the Permanent Court of International Justice": Extracts from testimony of Bishop Charles H. Brent, President A. Lawrence Lowell, Hon. George W. Wickersham, and others, Vol. VII, No. 2, 1924
Synopsis of the Geneva Protocol for the Pacific Settlement of International Disputes, n.d.
Secretary Hughes and The League of Nations by Raymond B. Fosdick, reprinted from the New York Times, 1924
The League of Nations, A Survey, (1920-25)
The International Labor Organization, Its Ideals and Results by E.J. Phelan, 1925
Covenant of the League of Nations with Amendments in Force, 1926
Report of Exhibit ( held for Leaders of Young People to Suggest Ways and Means of Cultivating and Stimulating Ideas of International Friendship and Good Will), 1925
Training in Summer Camps for World Co-operation, Educational Department, 1926
Essential Facts in regard to The League of Nations, The World Court and the International Labor Organization, Educational Publications No. 2, 1926
Essential Facts in regard to The League of Nations, The World Court and the International Labor Organization, The Educational Committee, 1934
World Peace Primer, H.S. Thurber Co., 1925
Willful Crimes by the Fakers Viz: The League of Nations (A Writ of Habeas Corpus for the Emperor of Germany, William the Second) by Countess Ida von Claussen, 1924
Articles (box 7, folders 8-11)
League of Nations: Report on the League since the Fourteenth Session of the Assembly, Part I, Geneva, 1934
High Commission for Refugees (Jewish and Other) Coming from Germany, 1934
League of Nations Information Section No. 7118, Geneva, 1934
League of Nations Information Section, Geneva, 1934
The Fifteenth Ordinary Session of the Assembly, Geneva: President Sandler, September 13th, 1934 at 11 a.m.
The Fifteenth Ordinary Session of the Assembly, Geneva: President Sandler, September 14th, 1934 at 10 a.m.
Speech delivered by M. Motta, Federal Councilor, First Delegate of the Swiss Confederation, Before the Sixth Committee on the Application of the U.S.S.R. to the League of Nations
League of Nations Information Section No. 7062, Sep 17 1934
League of Nations: The Fifteenth Ordinary Session of the Assembly, Verbatim Report of the Seventh Meeting Held at the Salle Du Conseil Général, Geneva, on Monday, September 17th, 1934 at 11 a.m. President: M. R.J. Sandler
League of Nations: The Fifteenth Ordinary Session of the Assembly, Verbatim Report of the Twelfth Meeting Held at the Salle Du Conseil Général,Geneva on Thursday, September 27th, 1934 at 10 a.m. President: M. R.J. Sandler
League of Nations Information Section No. 7112, Geneva, Sep 28 1934
Unnamed, Assembly Transcript(?) Reads: "The President: Interpretation: I therefore declare that the admission of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics to the League of Nations has been decided by the Assembly with the necessary majority…"
Fifteenth Assembly: Opening Speech by the President of the Council of the League of Nations
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Writings about Florence Guertin Tuttle
    - Manuscripts and drafts (Box 1)
      - Biographical writings and drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - "Journey to Geneva": manuscript of observations, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - "I Traveled Hopefully": manuscript and autobiography, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Articles and clippings about Florence Guertin Tuttle (including travel, League of Nations, Carrie Chapman Catt and Margaret Sanger), 1921-27 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Travel diary, engagement book, passport, and will, 1933-34 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs and postcards, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Memorabilia (invitations, programs, miscellaneous items and European trip memorabilia), circa 1920's-36 (Box 1, Folder 9-12)
  - Business: banks statements and miscellaneous items, 1917-36 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bible, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets and clippings, re: world affairs, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Individuals
    - Bartlett, Alice, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Berg, Portia Willis, 1921(?)-22 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Cecil, Robert, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Guertin, Henri ("Harry"), 1934-35 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Randall, Fay, 1921-22, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Tuttle, Day, 1921 (?), 1935-36 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Tuttle, Guertin, 1922-36 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Tuttle, Laura Lee, 1935-36 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - General
    - Family (Francis and others), 1921, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - A-D, 1918-36 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - E-J, 1920-39 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - K-Q, 1920-36 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - R-Q, 1918-39 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Telegrams, 1922-36 (European trip) (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence and invitations (mostly 1939) (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Miscellaneous (including League of Nations Non-Partisan Association), 1921-27 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous (including European trip, 1936), 1921-34, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS AND SPEECHES
  - Writings
    [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS]
    - The Awakening of Woman: reviews, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "Woman and Peace": manuscript, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Women and World Federation
      - Manuscript (chaps. 1 - 5), 1918 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Manuscript (chaps. 6 - 9), 1919 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence, royalties, etc. 1920 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "Women and World Problems": manuscript and notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Articles
    - From magazines and newspapers, 1920-22 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Speeches: League of Nations, disarmament, war, etc., 1922-24 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- SERIES IV. ORGANIZATIONS AND CONFERENCES
  - American Association for International Cooperation: correspondence, 1921-23 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - American Peace Award, 1923-24 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - American Union against Militarism: correspondence, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Berry School: pilgrims, 1934-35 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Birth control: population conference, Geneva, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Congressional Union for Woman Suffrage: correspondence, 1917-22 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Democratic National Convention: correspondence, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Foreign Policy Association
    - Correspondence, 1921-35 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - The Bulletin (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Pamphlets (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - International Federation of Business and Professional Women, 1935-36 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - International peace organizations: pamphlets, correspondence, and miscellaneous items, 1924-39 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - League for Political Education: Countess Karolyi and the Earl of Lytton, 1924-35 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - League of Nations (Box 4)
    [see boxes 5-8]
  - National Committee on the Cause and Cure of War, 1926-31 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - New York League of Business and Professional Women: tribute dinner, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - New York State League of Women Voters: correspondence, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Peace organizations and articles, 1923-26 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Unitarian Laymen's League, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Woman's Peace Party of New York City, 1917
    - Open letter to President Wilson (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Women's Trade Union League, 1923-26 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Women's University Club: New York branch, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - World Court, 1922-26 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous organizations, 1936-46 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - League of Nations
    - League of Nations Association, 1936-39 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Disarmament Conference, Geneva, 1932
      - Speech by Tuttle, articles, and correspondence (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Scrapbook
        [see box 8]
    - Education committee, 1925 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Geneva Conference, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - General information, 1925-27 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Headway (periodical), 1924-26 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - League of Nations Herald, 1924-25 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - International Federation: Glasgow Congress, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Monthly summary, 1920-26 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Pamphlets, 1923-36 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - General: reports, minutes, memoranda, and correspondence, 1923-35 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Non-Partisan Association
      - Memoranda, 1923-27 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - History, procedures, etc., 1923-27 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence, 1923-26 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Publications, 1923-27 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Reports, 1923-26 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Woman's Pro-League Council, 1921-24
      - Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence (Tuttle) (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Minutes, procedures, etc. (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - Publications (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - League of Nations School, 1934-35 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Invitations, 1935, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Publications
      - League of Nations News (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Pamphlets (Box 7, Folder 3-7)
        [see Appendix for title list]
      - Reports (Box 7, Folder 8-11)
    - Disarmament Conference, Geneva: scrapbook, 1932 (Box 8)
- SERIES V. OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Posters advertising The Awakening of Woman, circa 1915, and Give My Love to Maria, 1917 (2 copies) (Mapcase Flat file)
  - Political cartoons (2) "from disarmament conference at Geneva by the famous official cartoonists of the League of Nations, Derso and Kalen" and description, 1932, 1934 (Mapcase Flat file)